Hello English learners, welcome back to another advanced lesson here at
English Pod, my name is Marco and I'm Erica and today we're going to be
back in the office that's right we are listening in as somebody gets a
little bit of trouble from their boss or being a bit late on a project.
Alright so we're going to be at the office somebody misses
a deadline and so well how do you handle the situation
what can you do to explain yourself and what language can
you actually use to talk about mis deadlines and late work.
Alright so let's see
why this person missed
the deadline and let's
find out what happens.
And so I just wanted
to check in with you
and find out where
we are with this project.
As you know you missed a fairly significant
deadline last week and this will negatively
impact the team's ability to move forward
with the next stages of this project.
I know I'm really sorry that I missed a deadline but really it
wasn't my fault. You see we had all of these unexpected technical
problems at the last minute and I couldn't get into the database and
extract the kind of information that I needed for the data analysis.
You know if the tech guys
would have done their job and
kept the CRM stable then I
wouldn't have missed my deadline.
Come on and excuse like that is tantamount to lying. You're
essentially blaming the tech team for your time management
issues rather than accepting responsibility for the fact
that you are procrastinating for the past two weeks.
No I'm not trying to pass the buck here. I know
it was me who was ultimately responsible for
getting this done but the thing is I could have
finished on time if the system hadn't gone down.
No with everything I've got going on now
I can't afford to waste time dealing with
technical problems. I've got a lot of my
plate and there are only 24 hours in a day.
I'm not going to accept this excuse.
You're using these small technical glitches
as a crutch and trying to rationalize
the fact that you've missed your deadline.
Look we have standards
and I expect you to live
up to those standards.
No more phony excuses.
If you're in over your head you
tell me no more missed deadlines.
Now I want that data
on my desk by 9 a.m.
Well it sounds like this guy isn't really
accepting a lot of the responsibility for his
missed deadline. Exactly. Well apparently he's
explaining that it wasn't only his fault right.
Yeah so some technical problems but you know
he used a lot of pretty pretty interesting
language and I think it'll help us to
look at that now in language takeaway.
Language takeaway. Alright
so on language takeaway today
we have five words and
let's start with the first one.
Alright well the boss is not really
happy with the excuse that the
employee was giving and he said an
excuse like that is tantamount to lying.
tantamount to something. Okay so if an excuse
like that is tantamount to lying what is
what is he trying to say here? Basically
it's the same as or it's almost the same as.
So similar to. So if I say tantamount to
something else so how would I use it?
You know Marco taking my computer
without asking is tantamount to stealing.
Okay so even though I'm not actually stealing and you're taking
it home with me. Yeah it is almost like stealing. Yeah and
the interesting grammatical thing here is that we almost
always use a gerund right after so tantamount to verbae and g.
Okay tantamount to stealing,
tantamount to lying, tantamount to killing.
Okay well on that happy note
let's go on to our next word.
Now the boss was really
unhappy with the employee for
procrastinating,
procrastinating, procrastinating.
So the verb is to procrastinate
and when you procrastinate
you say oh I'll do it
later I'll do it tomorrow.
Okay so you kind of delay things
or you leave it for another day.
Yeah alright very good
so to procrastinate.
A favorite verb amongst college
students. I actually thought
for a little while that
procrastinate was to have babies.
Oh okay it's kind of similar what's it what's the
word? Procreate. Procreate so for a while I always
thought that procrastinate was like having babies
like why are you procrastinating and I'm like I'm not.
Well glad you got that straight.
So yes our listeners procrastinate
is not the same as procreate.
Okay I learned that the hard way.
Yes well it sounds like you had a little
bit of a glitch in your understanding
of language and that's our next phrase.
So in the dialogue they were
talking about some glitches
with the system. A glitch in
the system. Okay so a glitch.
Now this is a comment among computers right? A glitch is
an error. Right so when you're talking about a glitch and
you're talking about computers it's an error a mistake
but we also use it to talk about any unexpected problem.
A small unexpected problem.
Okay so a small glitch.
Yeah there was a glitch in our
plan and we arrived 10 minutes late.
Or I can say this movie
has a glitch in the story.
So there's a small problem in a story that doesn't
make sense. Exactly. All right so the employee
was blaming his lateness on these small technical
glitches but the boss didn't believe this right?
The boss said you're trying
to rationalize the fact that
you missed the deadline.
Okay to rationalize to rationalize.
So the boss is saying that he's trying to rationalize. So that means is he trying
to make sense of it? Well this is an interesting psychological word and when
you rationalize something you think about it or describe it like especially
some bad behavior in a way that makes it seem better or proper or more sensible.
So you're trying to convince yourself. Yeah
you're telling other people but you're also
telling yourself that it's better. Okay or
that you're right when you're actually wrong.
Yes. Okay so he was trying to rationalize the fact
that he missed the deadline. So he was trying to
explain to the boss and also kind of make himself
believe that it wasn't really his fault when it was.
Now because this is a
little bit of a difficult concept
to understand I think we
should hear some examples.
You can't rationalize your son's behavior
by saying he's going through a hard time.
Example two.
As much as I tried I couldn't rationalize
buying such an expensive pair of shoes.
Example three. You know it was the wrong
thing to do. Stop trying to rationalize it.
Okay so clear as daylight now this word
rationalize. All right and our final word so
the boss really wasn't happy with these
excuses and he said no more phony excuses.
Okay phony.
So phony is basically false or
fake. Right so a phony statement.
A phony watch. Okay a fake watch.
Yeah not a phony watch but a phony watch.
So a lot of great words in this dialogue
but as you mentioned we also saw
some very interesting phrases
that we can use in situations like this.
So why don't we start
now with fluency builder.
Well you know one of the interesting
things about English is that we have a
lot of ways to make things sound
more direct, less direct harder or softer.
And in this dialogue there are a
few examples of how we use softening
words to but to do the opposite
to actually make it a little strong.
Okay so why don't we start with
the first paragraph in the first part
of the dialogue he said you
missed a fairly significant deadline.
A fairly significant deadline.
Now this word fairly kind of sort of.
So it's not very significant
it's kind of significant.
Yeah but in this context
when the person is saying it it
just sounds a little bit softer
but your understanding is.
It's a very important deadline.
Okay a very important deadline.
So another similar example
of this is the boss was
saying you're essentially
blaming the tech team.
Okay you're essentially blaming.
So essentially is like
basically or pretty much.
So it sounds a little
softer but what he's
actually really saying
is you're doing this.
Right so instead of saying you're
blaming the tech team he adds this word
essentially to kind of say well
basically you're saying it's their fault.
Yeah but the context or
you understand that it's
actually very direct and
he's saying it's your fault.
Yeah so he's saying you're
almost blaming the tech
team but what he means is
you're blaming the tech team.
Now our third phrase is very interesting
because it's kind of like a saying.
That's right so the employee says
I'm not trying to pass the buck here.
I'm not trying to pass the buck.
Now what's the buck?
A dollar bill.
So he's what I understand
that he's saying I'm not trying
to blame somebody else or
pass the blame onto someone else.
But you can think about it like this.
Like imagine he had some
fake or phony money right?
And he wants to pass that on to the
next person so he doesn't get in trouble.
Okay.
So I'm not trying to pass the buck.
I'm not trying to pass the blame.
Put the responsibility on someone else.
Very good.
But you know what he really means here?
What?
I am trying to do this.
Because he knew that
it was a fake dollar bill.
Yeah.
Now the fourth one is interesting as
well because it's kind of like a metaphor.
He said the boss said you're using
the small technical glitches as a crutch.
So using something as a crutch.
Now the crutch is a... You know
when you break your leg, you use
those wood in your
metal sticks to walk with?
Okay to help you walk.
So the boss is basically saying
you're using these technical
glitches as an excuse or as an
aid to why you missed the deadline.
Yeah.
So if you think about it like
this, some people might say,
"Okay, if you walk with a
crutch, then you won't succeed.
" Right?
Because whatever.
So this guy, this employee,
is basically saying,
"Yes, I know that I
should meet deadlines.
" But these problems, these glitches are
like my crutch that make me not succeed.
Okay, so he's trying to just make excuses.
So, um, God, Margaret, that was
a little bit difficult to understand.
Do you think we should
give a couple more examples?
Yeah, I think some more
examples would be very
useful, so let's listen to
a couple of them now.
Example one.
I realized that I was using alcohol
as a crutch to get through the day.
Example two.
I think Bill's very capable
of being successful,
but he uses his
disability as a crutch.
Example three.
Stop using your weight
as a crutch, just because
your bit fat doesn't mean
you can't get a great job.
All right, so a lot of great
phrases, great words, and well, I
think it's time for us to listen
to this dialogue for the last time.
And then we'll come back and talk
about this aspect of meeting deadlines.
And so I just wanted
to check in with you
and find out where
we are with this project.
As you know, you missed a fairly significant
deadline last week, and this will negatively
impact the team's ability to move forward
with the next stages of this project.
I know, I'm really sorry that I missed a
deadline, but really, it wasn't my fault.
You see, we had all of these unexpected technical
problems at the last minute, and I couldn't
get into the database and extract the kind of
information that I needed for the data analysis.
You know, if the tech guys
would have done their job and
kept the CRM stable, then I
wouldn't have missed my deadline.
Oh, come on, and excuse like that is tantamount to lying.
You're essentially blaming the tech team for your time
management issues, rather than accepting responsibility for
the fact that you are procrastinating for the past two weeks.
No, I'm not trying to pass the buck here. I know
it was me who was ultimately responsible for
getting this done, but the thing is, I could have
finished on time if the system hadn't gone down.
But you know that everything I've got going
on now, I can't afford to waste time dealing
with technical problems. I've got a lot of my
plate, and there are only 24 hours in a day.
I'm not going to accept this excuse.
You're using these small technical glitches
as a crutch and trying to rationalize
the fact that you've missed your deadline.
Look, we have standards,
and I expect you to live
up to those standards.
No more phony excuses.
If you're in over your head, you
tell me, no more missed deadlines.
Now, I want that data
on my desk by 9am.
This employee got in a lot of
trouble for missing his deadline.
Exactly. I think it's a very
important aspect of not only Western
culture, but also in general,
assuming guilt when it's your fault.
In this case, we saw that
the employee didn't really
want to accept the
fact that he was his fault.
Yeah, he didn't say,
"Yeah, I know it was me,
I'm sorry, and this
is my plan to fix it."
Now, this is very important
among cultures because in some
cultures, the aspect of losing
face is so important, right?
Right.
So somebody may not
really want to assume guilt
or they have to because
it's part of the culture.
But what's the standard in
North American business practice?
I would say that you would
have to assume responsibility
and take responsibility
for your actions, right?
And say, "Yes, it's my fault
I did it, but I'm going to
get it fixed, or I'll do
it, or I'll make up for it.
" So some good business
tips here today in this lesson.
Now, remember if you have any
questions about the language or want to
tell us a little bit about how
you assume responsibility
in your culture, visit our
website at EnglishPod.com.
We're always there to help
you out and until next time.
Thanks for listening and goodbye.